Guide to the George Warren Arms Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
George Warren Arms collection
1848-1988
YCAL MSS 170
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.5
(8 boxes)
The George Warren Arms collection consists of letters, manuscripts and subject files documenting research on 19th and early 20th century American authors. Series I, Correspondence, is organized into two subseries for General and Third-Party Correspondence. General Correspondence consists of correspondence between Arms and writers, scholars, booksellers, autograph dealers and others. The Third-Party Correspondence consists of letters by 19th and early 20th century American authors collected by Arms. Included are George William Curtis, James Thomas Fields, Mary Eleanor Wilkins Freeman, William Dean Howells, James Russell Lowell, Charles Eliot Norton and Calvin Ellis Stowe. Series II, Writings of Others, consists chiefly of work by Arms' students dating from the 1960s. Series III, Subject Files, contains bibliographic information, chiefly printed fragments from dealer catalogs, and biographical and critical notes.
Arms, George, 1912-1992
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The George Warren Arms Collection was acquired through purchases on Eugene G. O'Neill Memorial and Sinclair Lewis book funds.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 8: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
GEORGE WARREN ARMS (1912-1992)
George Warren Arms was born February 1, 1912, in La Grande, Oregon to George Wells and Marguerite Shattuck Arms. He was educated at Princeton University, the Universities of Zurich and Munich, and New York University. He taught in preparatory schools from 1933-38, at Bennett Junior College in 1939, at Mary Washington College as an assistant professor of English from 1939-44, and at the University of New Mexico as a professor of English from 1945 until his retirement.
Arms co-authored and co-edited numerous books on American writers and several on William Dean Howells, including Five Interviews with William Dean Howells (1943), A Bibliography of William Dean Howells (1948) and Selected Letters (1979-83). He also wrote The Fields were Green: A New View of Bryant, Whittier, Holmes, Lowell, and Longfellow (1953) and served as co-editor of The Explicator.
Arms married Elizabeth Tanner on June 27, 1936. He died January 1, 1992, in Albuquerque, New Mexico.
Scope and Contents
The George Warren Arms Collection consists of letters, manuscripts and subject files documenting the life and work of George Warren Arms. The collection spans the years 1848-1988.
The collection is housed in 8 boxes and organized into three series: Correspondence, Writings of Others and Subject Files. Box 8 contains Restricted Fragile Papers.
Series I, Correspondence, is organized into two subseries: General Correspondence and Third-Party Correspondence.
General Correspondence, housed in boxes 1-2, consists of correspondence between Arms and writers, scholars, booksellers, autograph dealers and others. Arms wrote extensively on William Dean Howells, and much of the correspondence pertains to Howells and other 19th and early 20th century American writers.
Carbon copies of letters from Arms to others are present in much of this subseries.
Third-Party Correspondence, housed in boxes 3-5, consists of letters, mostly ALS dating from the mid-late 19th century, which Arms collected for his own research and for research by students in courses at the University of New Mexico. Letters are arranged alphabetically by author and then by correspondent. Included are George William Curtis, James Thomas Fields, Mary Eleanor Wilkins Freeman, William Dean Howells, James Russell Lowell, Charles Eliot Norton and Calvin Ellis Stowe.
Typescript copies of letters and biographical notes are present in parts of this subseries. Specifically, many of the Howells letters are accompanied by typescript copies, and many of the Fields, Freeman, Howells and Norton letters are accompanied by notes on small index cards.
Series II, Writings of Others, housed in box 6, is arranged alphabetically by author and then by title. There is a draft fragment by Howells entitled "Literary Friends and Acquaintance," as well as a letter to the editor by Charles Eliot Norton. Otherwise, the writings subseries consists of work by Arms' students dating from the early and mid 1960s. There are explications of letters from Ralph Waldo Emerson, Henry Wadsworth Longfellow, Henry James, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Horace Elisha Scudder and James Huneker, in addition to those from writers represented in the Third-Party Correspondence.
Series III, Subject Files, housed in box 7, is arranged alphabetically by name. The Subject Files contain bibliographic information, predominantly printed fragments from bookdealers' catalogs, biographical and critical notes, and, in a few cases, copies of letters. Once again the emphasis is on 19th century American authors. Authors not found or mentioned in earlier subseries are William E. Channing, F. Marion Crawford, Edgar Fawcett and Charles Warren Stoddard.
Restricted Fragile Papers are housed in box 8.
American literature -- 19th century; American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 19th century -- Archives; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Arms, George, 1912-1992; Curtis, George William, 1824-1892; Fields, James Thomas, 1817-1881; Freeman, Mary Eleanor Wilkins, 1852-1930; Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920; Lowell, James Russell, 1819-1891; Meynell, Francis, 1891-1975; Norton, Charles Eliot, 1827-1908; Stowe, C. E. (Calvin Ellis), 1802-1886; Swallow, Alan, 1915-1966; Wellek, René, 1903-1995; Wilson, Edmund, 1895-1972
- Correspondence, 1848-1988; Series I; 1.88' (5 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is organized into two subseries and arranged alphabetically within each subseries by name of correspondent.
  - GENERAL
    - "A" General, 1941, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Abramson, Ben, 1942-43 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Aderman, Ralph M., 1969 Apr (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Includes page from printed catalogue
    - Anderson, Charles Roberts, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Anderson, Frederick, 1971-75 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Includes copy of letter from "Fuller" to Samuel L. Clemens
    - Arnavon, Cyrille, 1968, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "B" General, 1938-83 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Bell, Quentin, 1964 Jun 10 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Bellow, Saul, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Includes letter from Kenney Withers
    - Benjamin, Mary A., 1957, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Boyd, Julian P. (Julian Parks), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bryant, William Cullen, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Includes clipping from printed catalogue
    - Burlingame, Robert, 1962-78 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Burnshaw, Stanley, 1953 Jan (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Cargill, Oscar, 1938-61, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Includes review of Francis Hopkinson's essay "On Whitewashing"
    - Caron, Leo J., 1962, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Includes copy of letter from Henry M. Arms and pages from printed catalogues
    - Cerf, Bennett, 1944 Apr 13 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Clark, Harry Hayden, 1946-48 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Includes letter from Clark to "Kirk"
    - Clark, Walter Van Tilburg, 1954 Jan 14 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Clemens, Cyril, 1942 Jul 2 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Crowley, John William, 1974-76 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Includes page proof from George Cabot Lodge
    - Currier, Thomas Franklin, 1946, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Includes letters from Mrs. Currier and photocopies of map, book cover and title page to Mitchell's School Atlas
    - "D" General, 1975 Jul 13 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Dashiell, Margaret, 1939 Nov 9 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Du Maurier, Daphne, Dame, 1964 Jun 2 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Eberhart, Richard, 1947-74, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Includes correspondence between Eberhart and J. Edwin Whitesell, poems and notes
    - Edel, Leon, 1961 Jun (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Includes letter from Edel to William M. Gibson
    - Elwin, Malcolm, 1964 Jun 13 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - "F" General, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Fergusson, Francis, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Includes correpondence with Louis Glen Locke and letters from Kenney Withers
    - Filler, Louis, 1949 Nov 27 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Garland, Hamlin, 1940 Jan (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Garnett, Angelica, 1964 Jul, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Gentry, Helen, 1951 Mar (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Gibson, William Merriam, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Greenhood, David, 1951 Jul 28 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - "H" General, 1939-73 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Harper & Brothers, 1939-42 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Harris, Mark, 1949-72 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Harvard College Library, 1954 Jun (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Hellman, George S. (George Sidney), 1938-[39?] (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Hicks, John Donald, 1966-67 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Hilderbrand, Grace H., 1960 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      Includes notes and copies of letters relating to Alonzo Crittenden and William Gilmore Simms
    - Hilen, Andrew R., 1972 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Hoffman, Daniel, 1951-63 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Honig, Edwin, 1951-64 (Box 1, Folder 46)
      Includes poem
    - Howells, Mildred, 1938-52 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Howells, W. W. (William White), 1947-88 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      Includes letter from Howells to Justina Shoemaker
    - Hughes, Emrys, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Jablonowski, James L., 1974 Jan (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - "K" General, 1938-48 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Katz, Joseph, 1975 Oct 26 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Keleher, W. A., 1952-78 (Box 1, Folder 53)
      Related Archival Materials note
      See also: St. Paul's School (Concord, N.H.), Box 2, folder 90
    - Kendrick, Brent L., 1976 Mar (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Klinkowitz, Jerome, 1984-85, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 55)
      Includes photocopy of letter from W. D. Howells and notes
    - "L" General, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Leary, Lewis Gaston, 1962 Mar (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Levenson, J. C. (Jacob Clavner), 1981 Aug (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Liljegren, S. B., 1951-52 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Lueders, Edward G., 1960 Feb 9 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - "M" General, 1952-67 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Meynell, Francis, Sir, 1964 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Modern Language Association of America, 1940-45 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Mordell, Albert, 1908-42 (Box 1, Folder 64)
      Includes letters from W. D. Howells and book jacket to Dante and Other Waning Classics
    - Morgan, Arthur E., 1931 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Munby, A. N. L. (Alan Noel Latimer), 1964 May 19 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Murdock, Kenneth Ballard, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - New Directions Publishing Corp, 1948-49 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - New England Quarterly, 1944, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - The New Yorker, 1950 May (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - "O" General, 1972 Oct 9 (Box 2, Folder 71)
      Includes copy of letter from Christopher Pearse Cranch to Oliver Wendell Holmes
    - "P" General, 1964 Jul (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Pearson, Norman Holmes, 1942-64, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Peden, William Harwood, 1957 Mar (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Pierpont Morgan Library, 1980 Jun (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Poetry, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - "R" General, 1940, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - R. R. Bowker Company, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Rago, Henry, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Random House (Firm), 1952 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Rinehart & Company, Inc., 1957 (Box 2, Folder 81)
      Includes letters to Farrar, Straus and Cudahy and Edmund Wilson
    - Roberts, Octavia, 1957 Feb 18 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - Rollins, Carl Purington, 1954 Apr (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Rosenthal, M. L. (Macha Louis), 1957-65 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Ross, Adelaide, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - Rothenberg, Gunther Erich, 1966 Oct 26 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - Rubin, Louis Decimus, 1955-56 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - Rusk, Ralph L. (Ralph Leslie), 1953-77, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 88)
      Includes copy of letter from Ralph Waldo Emerson to Sylvia Watson
    - "S" General, 1939-74 (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - St. Paul's School (Concord, N.H.), 1952 (Box 2, Folder 90)
      See also: Keleher, W. A., Box 1, folder 53
    - Saturday Review, 1945-46 (Box 2, Folder 91)
    - Schiffman, Joseph, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 92)
      Includes copy of letter from Edward Bellamy to "Baxter"
    - Schwab, Arnold T., 1921-75, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 93)
    - Scott, Winfield Townley, 1961, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 94)
    - Sears, Clara Endicott, 1939 Nov 21 (Box 2, Folder 95)
    - The Sewanee Review, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 96)
    - Smith, Bernard, 1944 Jun 22 (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - Stegner, Wallace Earle, 1965 Jan (Box 2, Folder 98)
    - Stern, Madeleine B., 1960 Feb (Box 2, Folder 99)
    - Streit, Clarence K. (Clarence Kirshman), 1939 (Box 2, Folder 100)
    - Swallow, Alan, 1949-54 (Box 2, Folder 101-102)
      Includes correspondence with Josephine Miles and letter from Mark Schorer
    - "T" General, 1964 Jun 13 (Box 2, Folder 103)
    - Thorp, Willard, 1939 Apr 24 (Box 2, Folder 104)
    - Tilton, Eleanor M. (Eleanor Marguerite), 1977, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 105)
    - Tomlinson, Charles, 1962-72 (Box 2, Folder 106)
    - Turner, Arlin, 1967-69, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 107)
    - Vandersee, Charles, 1979 May (Box 2, Folder 108)
      Includes copy of letter from Henry Adams to Mrs. Winthrop Chandler
    - Viking Press, 1940-41 (Box 2, Folder 109)
    - "W" General, 1939, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 110)
    - Wagenknecht, Edward, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 111)
    - Walston, Henry David Leonard George Walston, Baron, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 112)
    - Waters, Frank, 1955 Jul (Box 2, Folder 113)
    - Wellek, René, 1951-66 (Box 2, Folder 114-115)
      Includes letters from Kenney Withers
    - Wilbur, Richard, 1953 May 9 (Box 2, Folder 116)
    - Wilder, Amos Niven, 1956-68 (Box 2, Folder 117)
    - Williams, Stanley Thomas, 1949-52 (Box 2, Folder 118)
    - Wilson, Edmund, 1950 May 23 (Box 2, Folder 119)
    - Wilson, Keith, 1976 Mar 12 (Box 2, Folder 120)
    - Withers, Kenney, 1966 Sep 19 (Box 2, Folder 121)
    - Woolf, Leonard, 1950 Nov 20 (Box 2, Folder 122)
    - "Y" General, 1979 Mar 19 (Box 2, Folder 123)
    - Zangwill, O. L. (Oliver Louis), 1964 May 19 (Box 2, Folder 124)
  - THIRD-PARTY
    - Curtis, George William
      - To Acton, ----, 1865 Nov 24 (Box 3, Folder 125)
      - To Allen, ----, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 126)
      - To Barnard, James, 1872 Dec 23 (Box 3, Folder 127)
      - To Brown, ----, 1886 Sep 5 (Box 3, Folder 128)
      - To Campbell, ----, 1880 Dec 8 (Box 3, Folder 129)
      - To Chadwick, ----, 1883 Mar 1 (Box 3, Folder 130)
      - To Chase, ----, 1865 May 18 (Box 3, Folder 131)
      - To Clothier, W., 1860 Dec 22 (Box 3, Folder 132)
      - To Crosier, ----, 1865 Sep 30 (Box 3, Folder 133)
      - To Davis, ----, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 134)
      - To De Forest, ----, 1867 Sep 16 (Box 3, Folder 135)
      - To Drake, ----, 1876 Feb 28 (Box 3, Folder 136)
      - To Fields, ----, 1861-72 (Box 3, Folder 137)
      - To [Grosman?], ----, 1883 Nov 12 (Box 3, Folder 138)
      - To [Haynes?], ----, 1869 Mar 25 (Box 3, Folder 139)
      - To Howland, H., 1858 Nov 8 (Box 3, Folder 140)
      - To King, Horatio, 1886 Aug 29 (Box 3, Folder 141)
      - To Mayo, W., 1860 Nov 21 (Box 3, Folder 142)
      - To Raymond, ----, 1860 Nov 8 (Box 3, Folder 143)
      - To Sanborn, ----, 1868 Sep 23 (Box 3, Folder 144)
      - To [Tolman?], ----, 1870 Sep 21 (Box 3, Folder 145)
      - To Tucker, ----, 1869 Apr 9 (Box 3, Folder 146)
      - To Ward, ----, 1890 Nov 13 (Box 3, Folder 147)
      - To unidentified, 1855-85 (Box 3, Folder 148)
    - Fields, James Thomas
      - To Cist, Lewis J. (Lewis Jacob), 1862, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 149)
      - To Coolidge, H. H., 1873 Apr 30 (Box 3, Folder 150)
      - To Parton, James, 1867 Feb 15 (Box 3, Folder 151)
      - To Poore, Benjamin Perley, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 152)
      - To Putnam, George Palmer, 1856 Apr 12 (Box 3, Folder 153)
      - To Stone, William L. (William Leete), 1872 Dec 18 (Box 3, Folder 154)
      - To Towle, George M. (George Makepeace), 1864, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 155)
      - To Tuller, F., 1854 Jan 31 (Box 3, Folder 156)
      - To unidentified, 1865-76 (Box 3, Folder 157)
    - Freeman, Mary Eleanor Wilkins
      - To Authors Club (Boston, Mass.), 1906 Jun 12 (Box 3, Folder 158)
      - To Breck, Edwin S., 1892 Jul 18 (Box 3, Folder 159)
      - To Harper & Brothers, 1894, 1905 (Box 3, Folder 160)
      - To Iribuer, Helen C., 1908 Nov 11 (Box 3, Folder 161)
      - To Knight, Joseph, 1891-95 (Box 3, Folder 162)
      - To Miller, ----, 1898 Feb 8 (Box 3, Folder 163)
      - To Williams, ----, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 164)
      - To unidentified, 1892, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 165)
    - Howells, William Dean
      - To "A", 1876-1912 (Box 3, Folder 166)
        Includes letter from C. F. Adams Jr. to Howells
      - To "B", 1873-1915 (Box 3, Folder 167-168)
        Includes clipping of Howells
      - To Bacheller, Irving, 1895 Nov 23 (Box 3, Folder 169)
      - To Batchelder, [Samuel?], 1869 May 29 (Box 3, Folder 170)
      - To Boltwood, Edward, 1899 Jul 23 (Box 3, Folder 171)
      - To Bowles, J. M. (Joseph Moore), 1887 Sep 8 (Box 3, Folder 172)
      - To "C", 1886-1919, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 173-174)
      - To Cawein, Madison [Julius?], 1891 Sep 20 (Box 3, Folder 175)
      - To Century Company, 1891 Oct 30 (Box 3, Folder 176)
      - To Century Illustrated Monthly Magazine, 1896-1900 (Box 3, Folder 177)
        Includes letter from R. U. Johnson to Howells
        See also: Gilder, Richard Watson, Box 3, folders 185-188
      - To "D", 1888-1916 (Box 3, Folder 178)
      - To "E", 1890-1910 (Box 3, Folder 179)
      - To Eliot, Mrs. Charles William, 1884 Dec 10 (Box 3, Folder 180)
      - To "F", 1884-1902 (Box 3, Folder 181)
      - To Fields, Mrs. [James Thomas?], 1875 Jul 18 (Box 3, Folder 182)
      - To "G", 1903 (Box 3, Folder 183)
      - To Garrison, F. J., 1876-80 (Box 3, Folder 184)
        Includes photo of Howells
      - To Gilder, Richard Watson, 1886-1907 (Box 3, Folder 185-188)
        See also: Century Illustrated Monthly Magazine, Box 3, folder 177
      - To "H", 1867-1913 (Box 3, Folder 189-190)
      - To Harper & Brothers, 1904-14 (Box 4, Folder 191-197)
        Includes letters from F. A. Duneka to Howells
      - To Harper's Magazine, 1918 Jun 7 (Box 4, Folder 198)
      - To Houghton, Mifflin and Company, 1886 Sep 29 (Box 4, Folder 199)
      - To Howells, Joe A., 1896-99 (Box 4, Folder 200)
      - To Jewett, Sarah Orne, 1878 Aug 14 (Box 4, Folder 201)
        Inscribed by Jewett
      - To Longfellow, [Ernest Wadsworth?], 1900 Nov 19 (Box 4, Folder 202)
      - To Longfellow, Samuel, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 203)
      - To Lowell, John A., 1892 Feb 14 (Box 4, Folder 204)
      - To "M", 1882-98 (Box 4, Folder 205)
      - To Marden Geo. A. (George Augustus), 1885 Jul 22 (Box 4, Folder 206)
      - To Munro, David A., 1899-1909 (Box 4, Folder 207-211)
        Includes lists of books by Robert Grant and Eden Phillpotts
      - To "N", 1885, 1890 (Box 4, Folder 212)
      - To Norton, Charles Eliot, 1894-99 (Box 4, Folder 213)
      - To "P", 1873-96 (Box 4, Folder 214)
      - To Parton, James, 1873-88, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 215)
      - To Phillips, Henry, 1881 Mar 29 (Box 4, Folder 216)
      - To Piatt, [John James?], 1874 May (Box 4, Folder 217)
        Includes letter on verso, dated 1874 May 18, from Moses Coit Tyler to Howells
      - To "R", 1884, 1891 (Box 4, Folder 218)
      - To Reeves, William Peters, 1910 Jul 6 (Box 4, Folder 219)
      - To Rideing, William H. (William Henry), 1900 Apr 27 (Box 4, Folder 220)
      - To Rood, Henry Edward, 1902-07 (Box 4, Folder 221-222)
      - To "S", 1896-1919 (Box 4, Folder 223)
      - To Sage, Dean, 1875-76 (Box 4, Folder 224)
        Includes card, dated 1954 Nov 17, from George A. Van Nosdall to George Warren Arms
      - To Saturday Evening Gazette, 1893 Dec 3 (Box 4, Folder 225)
      - To Sherman, Frank Dempster, 1891 Mar 25 (Box 4, Folder 226)
      - To Stedman, [Edmund Clarence?], 1876 Aug 20 (Box 4, Folder 227)
      - To Sterne, Stuart, 1877-79 (Box 4, Folder 228)
      - To "T", 1873-1903 (Box 4, Folder 229)
        Includes letter from Celia Thaxter to Howells
      - To Trübner & Co., 1882 Aug 21 (Box 4, Folder 230)
      - To Turner, Ross, 1900 Feb 4 (Box 4, Folder 231)
      - To Twain, Mark, 1883 Nov 17 (Box 4, Folder 232)
      - To "V", 1903 May 23 (Box 4, Folder 233)
      - To Vinton, Frederick Porter, 1883 Dec 21 (Box 4, Folder 234)
      - To "W", 1879-1912 (Box 5, Folder 235-236)
      - To Ward, [Samuel?], 1878 Jun 20 (Box 5, Folder 237)
      - To Whitney, [Anne?], 1890 Aug 17 (Box 5, Folder 238)
      - To unidentified, 1891-1902, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 239)
    - Lowell, James Russell
      - To Boyle, Cavendish, 1890 Apr 26 (Box 5, Folder 240)
      - To Boyle, Mary [Louisa?], 1888 Jan 16 (Box 5, Folder 241)
      - To Charles River National Bank, 1876 Nov 16 (Box 5, Folder 242)
        Contains signed check
      - To Cox, ----, 1881 Apr 23 (Box 5, Folder 243)
      - To Curtis, George William, 1870, 1876 (Box 5, Folder 244)
      - To Henry, ----, 1863 Dec 11 (Box 5, Folder 245)
      - To Higginson, Thomas Wentworth, 1858 Dec 9 (Box 5, Folder 246)
      - To Hill, Mrs. ----, 1881 May 23 (Box 5, Folder 247)
      - To Lang, Mrs. A., 1886 May 7 (Box 5, Folder 248)
      - To McDuffie, Rufus L., 1890 May 18 (Box 5, Folder 249)
      - To Smith, L. I., 1886 Jan 25 (Box 5, Folder 250)
    - Norton, Charles Eliot
      - To Bancroft, [George?], 1864 Jan 14 (Box 5, Folder 251)
      - To Brainerd, E., 1880 Jan 9 (Box 5, Folder 252)
      - To Brainerd, Ira H., 1889 May 25 (Box 5, Folder 253)
      - To Bridgman, S. E., 1898 Aug 30 (Box 5, Folder 254)
      - To Charles E. Merrill Publishing Company, 1890 Oct 17 (Box 5, Folder 255)
      - To Cole, Ashley Trimble, 1895 Nov 16 (Box 5, Folder 256)
      - To Denney, Henry G., 1879-80 (Box 5, Folder 257)
      - To Doane, William C., 1907 Nov 12 (Box 5, Folder 258)
      - To Ehrich, Louis R., 1893-1907 (Box 5, Folder 259)
      - To Ernst, ----, 1887 Jul 6 (Box 5, Folder 260)
      - To Gulick, F. C., 1899 Jan 12 (Box 5, Folder 261)
      - To Hall, E. H., 1886 Jan 22 (Box 5, Folder 262)
      - To Heathfield, H. D., 1905 Feb 15 (Box 5, Folder 263)
      - To Hopkins, Fred M., 1895 Apr 17 (Box 5, Folder 264)
      - To Johnson, Robert Underwood, 1890-98 (Box 5, Folder 265)
      - To Keet, A. E., 1895-96 (Box 5, Folder 266)
      - To Kent, J. C., 1907 Oct 9 (Box 5, Folder 267)
      - To Knight, Joseph, 1894 (Box 5, Folder 268)
      - To Mead, ----, 1881 Jul 20 (Box 5, Folder 269)
      - To Peabody, E. P., 1866 Aug 27 (Box 5, Folder 270)
      - To The Progress of the World, 1896 Jul 3 (Box 5, Folder 271)
      - To Robinson, Herman Foster, 1898 Dec 29 (Box 5, Folder 272)
      - To Smith, Minna, 1893 Nov 1 (Box 5, Folder 273)
      - To Smith, Joseph P., 1891 Feb 12 (Box 5, Folder 274)
      - To Stedman, Edmund [Clarence?], 1892 Sep 14 (Box 5, Folder 275)
      - To Thomas, Augustus, 1903 Jan 5 (Box 5, Folder 276)
      - To Thwing, ----, 1896-98 (Box 5, Folder 277)
      - To [Ticknor and Fields?], 1867 Jul 3 (Box 5, Folder 278)
      - To Walton, ----, 1884 Sep 27 (Box 5, Folder 279)
      - To unidentified, 1860, 1894 (Box 5, Folder 280)
    - Stowe, C. E. (Calvin Ellis)
      - To Cist, Charles, 1848 Jan 21 (Box 5, Folder 281)
- Writings of Others, 1901-67; Series II; 0.21' (1 box)
  Series II, Writings of Others, is arranged alpabetically by name of author.
  - Bennett, Arthur J.
    - "Introduction," explication of letter from Arlo Bates to "McDowell," mimeograph, annotated, 1965 Mar 9 (Box 6, Folder 282)